Britain had a problem.
Its prisons were packed.
It used to ship convicts to America, but
in 1776, America said no thanks and declared
independence.
So Britain looked at the far side of
the world and thought perfect.
In 1787, 11 ships called the first fleet
set sail carrying roughly 1500 people around 750
of them convicts.
After eight months at sea, they arrived.
And on the 26th of January, 1788 captain
Arthur Phillip raised the British flag at Sydney
Cove.
Some of these criminals, the youngest John Hudson
was a chimney sweep sentenced as a nine-year-old
for stealing clothes and a pistol.
The oldest was a woman in her eighties.
The colony nearly starved.
Nobody on board really knew how to farm
this soil.
And when the second fleet arrived, it was
so brutal.
It earned the nickname, the death fleet for
the Eora people of Sydney.
The arrival was catastrophic.
In 1789, smallpox swept through the harbor and
killed a huge share of the local Aboriginal
population.
Warriors like Pemulwuy led armed resistance against the
colony for over a decade.
And over the next 80 years, Britain would
send around 162,000 convicts to Australia.